

Nicolas Guinet

IT Consultant

Full stack desktop/web apps, Al/Dataviz on Finance & Industry - Paris

nguinet.pro@gmail.com +33 668 461 610





s mr.nicolas.guinet

🗜 github.com/guinetn

BNP PARIBAS SUEZ THALES IXBLUE AXA IM KEPLER EQUITIES ROCKWOOL ...

Successful IT Consultant offering +20 years of experience in demanding environments focused on client's satisfaction by producing cutting-edge designs, creative and performance-oriented approach. Well-organised and customer-focused with natural leadership and dirty hands.

Objective Help entities driven by challenges and tech edge

Education Master's Degree: DESS Systèmes électroniques et micro-ondes (1995) Paris VI

Skills

Be strong C, C++, C#, Python. MAUI (WPF), Winforms, Rust (2022)

Be safe Git, Github, Azure DevOps,

Javascript, NodeJS, Asp.net, React, NextJS, Vue, Svelte, TypeScript Be everywhere Have methods TDD, BDD, Solid, DRY, Design patterns, Functional programming Collaborate Azure devops, Agile, Scrum, Sharing tools: Google drive-docs...

Data is kev SqlServer, Oracle, MySql, SqLite, Sybase, MongoDB, GraphQL,. ORM: Ling, EF

Converted Json, Markdown, Mdx, Xml, Xslt, XPath,

Meet others OpenAPI, Swagger, Express, Serverless, Microservices

Fire and forget Kafka, RabbitMQ, MQ, Redis Cross the border Firebase, Azure, AWS, Netlify

Call friends Aspose, DevExpress, nuget, npm, yarn

Be on the line Android, Flutter, Pwa

Write your love VScode, Visual Studio, SublimeText, Android Studio Save time PowerShell, Bash, Gulp, Webpack, Rollup, Yeoman Scale up IaC (Docker, Kubernetes, Terraform), Octopus

Expendables Excel, Word, AddIns (vba), Vsto

Ok Google! AI, ML, R-Studio, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, ScikitLearn, TensorFlow, Julia EQ, FX, Futures, Options, Stock Lending, Repo, Bloomberg Data Licence Warren's world

Be curious Physics, electronics, robotics, statistics

On the wave Web3, Solidity

Work history

September 2021 - present: IT Consultant Self employed

Paris

Create a React PWA app https://hotellespalmiers.com/app/ Create a Jekyll (Ruby) app https://www.lamadison-imc.com/

Rewriting my blog from Hugo to Next JS https://nguinet-blog-guinetn.vercel.app/

March 2021 - July 2021 : IT Consultant

BNP Paribas

Paris group.bnpparibas

Create and extend Jupyter notebook widgets for BNP Paribas Global Market traders

- Python, Jupyter notebooks, Voilà, Jupyter-widgets, ag-grid

June 2017 - June 2020 : IT Consultant

Suez SmartSolutions

Paris suezsmartsolutions.com

They create innovative worldwide deployed numerical solution by collecting data (smart meters) for real time applications allowing to control (dashboards) and detect resource status.

Create C# applications & libraries (.Net, .NetCore) collecting/transforming data (Kafka, Rabbit, Oracle) to feed Suez's group backend software (asp.net dashboard, report).

Suez Digital Hub

They accelerate promising digital solutions for Suez group by mixing startup, team... on agile mode

Create a machine learning application with C# (data provider) and RStudio (RandomForest algo) to predict Suez water meter status (blocked, frozen...): Collecting, cleaning, labelling data, computation parallelization, model evaluation and creation of a NodeJs app to visually validating results (measures curve look vs prediction)

Technologies:

- * C# (.net Core), Asp.net, WCF, Git, Octopus, Azure devops
- * Kafka, Rabbit, MQ, Oracle, MariaDB, SQlite
- * Js, HTML, NodeJS, Postman
- * R Studio, Random forest, Python

April 2015 - February 2017 : IT Consultant TTS (Thalès Training & Simulation) Paris thalesgroup.com Activities in Aerospace, Defence and Security, Digital, Transportation...

- 1. In agile mode, development in C++ of a 'Reality H' helicopter simulator, the most advanced in the world (http://thls.co/KjBr309a6tL). Analysis of the real helicopter, data collection and systems implementation including failures. Working on all helicopter's systems (except the fms~carto, done by another team), I find the solution to get a real electrical system simulation (others were stuck), I also improve the cockpit benchmark web app (sockets based) to make functional tests (system+failure) before going into the real simulator.
- **2.** Creates the tablet version of the "instructor mission control" to lightweight the cockpit backseat instructor. **Technologies:** Windows/Unix, C++, C#, ClearCase, Scade, Mingwin, Angular2-Typescript, Jasmine, Protractor, Gulp, Jira, Maven

January 2015 : IT Consultant

IxBlue

Paris ixblue.com

Leading global provider of innovative solutions and services for navigation, positioning, and imaging. Civil and defence customers rely on our systems.

Develop application for managing Active Directory Encryption for the IxBlue Group.

Technologies: Asp.Net MVC5, Windows Service, Active Directory, Visual Studio, SVN

February 2013 - February 2014 : IT ConsultantGlobal multi-asset investor providing solutions for more secure investments. AXA Investment Managers London axa-im.fr

Development of several applications for the Front Office (REPO & Stock Lending)

- Define application specifications, exchange with traders, functional acquisition.
- Realisation of a WPF-MVVM-Unity-DevExpress-Aspose application to manage the daily operations of the front office. Development of script language to get simple scripts feeding application's reporting engine.
- Make a WPF-MVVM-Unity-DevExpress application to manage the fund distribution and generate PDF / Excel reports. This was a critical application for the group.
- Traders support. Following the intraday process. Front/Back office support on Excel / VBA add ins creation. **Technologies:** Visual Studio, Sql Server, GlobalOne, WPF-PRISM C# Excel AddIns

February 2010 - February 2013 : IT Consultant AXA Investment Managers Paris axa-im.fr

Front Office developments (EQ, FX, Futures, Options). Working with Traders and Portfolio managers to identify business needs and design appropriate solutions. Maintenance of existing processes, proposition to improve them. Development of several solutions in C#-WPF-AspNet for the traders of the Front Office.

Realisation of a task automation tool, script based, quickly adopted by other developers and other services.

Technologies: Visual Studio, Sql Server, Sybase, GlobalOne, C#, Winforms, ASP MVC - WPF-PRISM, XML

September 2009 - November 2009 : IT Consultant

ROCKWOOL

Paris rockwool.com

Leading manufacturer in sustainable non-combustible stone wool insulation.

Definition of specifications, understanding of functionality. Realisation of a Winforms application to calculate thermal insulation. Creating an innovative copy protection system to deploy the app on an USB key.

Technologies: Visual Studio, Winforms, C# / Personal graphic library

October 2009: IT Consultant

DFC PRODUCTIONS

Paris permisecole.com

Online traffic rules and driving licence training

Definition of the specifications and creation of a CMS (back-end) for the management of the website www.permisecole.com

Technologies: Visual Studio, Asp.Net 3.5, C#, Ling, Ajax

April 2009 - September 2009 : IT Consultant

OTC

Paris

Consortium Microsoft / Dexia / OTC / Zéliade Systems

OTC: organization and management consulting firm specialising in risk management and optimization, Zeliade is a software editor of financial libraries

Creation of the "Cris" (Credit Risk Services) web platform, a risk analysis tool for credit derivatives. Develop financial calculations with Zéliade team, authors of the ZQF library (financial library "all markets") **Technologies:** Visual Studio, Asp.Net 3.5, C#, Microsoft Charts, Ling, Silverlight, MVC & Ajax

January 2007 - March 2009 : IT Consultant

Dexia Crédit Local

Paris dexia.com

Bank of local authorities

- Under Bale II context, I've make a web application
 - Allowing the notation of the corporates (a "tax declaration" like grids sequence)
 Specification: accounting/notation formulas
 Implementation: Xml (notation grids were rendered dynamically as an "Excel like")

Implementation: Xml (notation grids were rendered dynamically as an "Excel like" html grid with xpath). Xml was a good choice as the specification often evolved and the interface wasn't dependent on.

Creation of the formulas computation engine

- Allowing a counterparties management system and the notation rapports visualisation.
- Maintain an existing insurance notation application.
- Evolve the web application «FBLC» (First Business Line Credit), a valorization and control tool for spreads on the bond market.

Technologies: Visual Studio 2005, Asp.Net 2.0, Winforms, C# 2.0 / XML, XSL, XSLT, Ajax / Oracle / Sql Server and Dts / Aspose Components

March 2006 - October 2006 : IT Consultant

Kepler Equities

Paris keplercheuvreux.c**om**

Leading European financial services company which specializes in Research, Execution, Fixed Income and Credit, Structured Solutions, Corporate Finance and Asset Management Services.

- **1.** Definition & specification of a C# reporting tool for the OMS (Order Management System) allowing to carry out the standard operations (split, merge, search of allocations) etc ... Internationalization of the application for the Italian and German offices of Kepler Equities.
- 2. Design of an Intranet in PHP to manage Kepler IT projects
- **3.** Analysis of "Bloomberg's Data Licence" interface and design tools using this interface to manage large volumes of 200MB / File data. Development of VBA scripts

Technologies: C#, Winforms, ADO.net, Multithreading, SQL Server, DTS, SYBASE, Excel, VBA, PHP, FTP, Bloomberg Console / Crystal Reports

September 2005 - February 2006 : Developer

Tests E Performance

La Seyne-sur-Mer

IT systems and software consulting

- **1.** Develop a "personal service management" application on the ARS (Action Request System) platform after having been trained on Remedy Software's ARS. The client was "La MAIF insurer, Niort France". Creation of addins in C# for the ARS platform
- **2.** Load tests for the French national lottery (Vitrolles-13) and Maroc Télécom with the software SilkPerformer and network analysis with Visualis software. Synthesis of results in Excel / VBA
- **3.** Definition of the spec. and realisation of the intranet of the company Test E Performance in PHP / MySQL **Technologies**: BMC Software/Remedy tools: ARS, DashBoard, FlashBoard, Visualis, SilkPerformer C#, Winforms, Excel, VBA, PHP, MySQL

June 2001 - August 2005 : IT Consultant

Create applications for several small local clients:

Accounting software (C++), Excel tools

Websites. www.hotellespalmiers.com www.grandhotelmoriaz.com ...

Telephone application based on SIP protocol for Webformance company to test phone existence.

Technologies: Kylix (C++ sous Linux) - Borland C++ Builder / Visual Studio / C#, Html, Css, Js

March 1998 - May 2001 : Developer / Webmaster

Webformance

Paris

Web hosting company, consulting in computer systems and software

- **1.** Development of SEO optimization software using Internet protocols (http, ftp, smtp, pop, news ...) to analyze the ranking of websites and make reports.
- 2. Realisation of all the software ~100 of the company

Development of ranking optimization software for web search engines

3. Realisation of 400 websites with the help of an automatic website generator that I've written.

Technologies: Borland C⁺⁺ Builder, Visual Basic, ADO, MS Office, Access, VBA, JavaScript, Perl, Java, Http

March 1997 - March 1998 : Developer

COMSEC / SOGESEC

Nice

Industrial manufacturer of alarm guard systems

Analysis, definition of specifications and creation of softwares to remote monitoring and analyze the signals coming from alarm systems sensors (lifts, alarm intrusion, liquid level ...). Implementation of different manufacturer protocols. Some developments in assembly language

Realisation of software for electronic test benches.

Technologies: Visual Basic, Access, Micro Controller PLM 51

May 1996 - June 1996: Internship (end of DESS)

ONERA

Palaiseau

The French aeronautics, space and defence research lab. (National Office for Aerospace Studies and Research)

Study internship context and define/write mathematical specification (Latex)

Development of a software for the numerical calculation of the mutual influences between wired antennas: distribution of E/M fields. Design of mathematical formulas, algorithms and numerical calculations

Technologies: Fortran, Unix, Gnuplot, Latex

Education

UNIVERSITÉ PIERRE ET MARIE CURIE (Paris VI)

1995 Master's degree (DESS) "Systèmes Électroniques et Informatiques"

UNIVERSITÉ DE TOULON ET DU VAR (Var, 83)

1994 BS (Maitrise) "Electronique – Informatique - Automatique"

1993 BS - Bachelor of Science - (Licence) "Electronique - Informatique - Automatique"

1992 Diploma of Higher Education (DEUG A) "Science de la matière, option physique-chimie"

1989 Lycée Jean-Aicard Hyères (Var, 83) High School Diploma on science (BAC D)

Personal

Languages: French (native), English (fluent written and spoken)

Driving Licence, Canadian Private Pilot Licence

Interest: machine learning, iot, geology, aviation, science